<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from a friend to a loyal subject where ever he is in England, Scotland, France or Ireland that is wise and faithful, valorous and couragious, for the great honour of God and our royal sovereign, Charles the Second, King of Great Britain / by J.V.</title>
            <author>J. V., 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65194</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23593</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07840653</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07840653</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40139</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65194)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40139)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1217:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from a friend to a loyal subject where ever he is in England, Scotland, France or Ireland that is wise and faithful, valorous and couragious, for the great honour of God and our royal sovereign, Charles the Second, King of Great Britain / by J.V.</title>
                  <author>J. V., 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. James for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40139:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER FROM A FRIEND TO A Loyal Subject, Where ever he is, in <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> that is Wiſe and Faithful, Valorous and Couragious, for the great Honour of God and our Royal Sovereign, <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Great Britain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>J. V.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. James</hi> for the Author, M.DC.LXXX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:40139:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40139:2"/>
            <head>A LETTER from a FRIEND TO A LOYAL SUBJECT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ALL that do profeſs the Faith ſhould Countenance and Encourage that Man that can manifeſt the Power of Faith, for the great Honour and Exaltation of a Kings Perſon, and the great Joy, Peace and Proſperity of many Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which will be brought about in a ſhort time, by that Man in whom the Lord of Hoſts doth make bare his Arm, to manifeſt his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Power among the Sons of Men, for the great Joy, Peace and Proſperity of them; for the Glory of his great Name, and to have the Devil and all the Workers of Evil brought to ſhame, that ſo his Goſpel, which is the Goſpel of Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, and the glad Tidings of Salvation, may run and be glorified among all Nations where it is not, and may flouriſh more and more where it is; that ſo the Heathens may be Converted, and Jews and Gentiles brought into one Fold: that ſo all Strife, Contention and Wars throughout the whole World may ceaſe, and among all People in all Nations a free Trade,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40139:3"/>great Joy, and a laſting Peace, which will be brought about in this Generation, for <hi>Englands</hi> great Honour and Exaltation, and for the great Shame, Contempt and Terror of all them that are for Strife and Contention, Sedition and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for Wars and Confuſion, by <hi>John Varney,</hi> a Friend to the Sons of Men, in the work of Faith, and the labour of Love for them, in ſuch high and honourable Work, that will prove pleaſant, profitable, and delightſome to many Perſons in all Nations, and Victorious, Glorious and Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Work, that will Crown the God of Heaven with much Glory among the Sons of Men, and our Royal Sovereign <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> with great Honour and Power over them, over all Heathen and Popiſh Kings, Prieſts, Princes and Emperors in the World.</p>
            <p>The words of our Lord and Saviour, when he was upon Earth with the Sons of Men, his words were words of Life and of Power among them; ſo are the words of that Man in all Generations, that doth believe in him, and can manifeſt the Power of Faith for him. Therefore let every Soul be ſubject to the higheſt Powers, for there is no Powers but of God; the Powers that be are ordained of God. Men and Devils have their Power from God, but the Power of Faith, it is the Power of God, it is not the Power of any Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Man, but it is the Power of God in Man, the Power of God with Man, the Power of God for Man, and the Power of God above Man, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40139:3"/>all the Powers of Hell, do what they can.</p>
            <p>The time is come, that all they that are Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the Proteſtant Religion, and to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that have ſlighted and undervalued Divine Faith, which is better than Strength or Weapons of War, or Silver or Gold, either a Perſon or a Nation will be aſhamed when they come to conſider and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that it is by Faith I ſtand; I ſtand in the Love and Favour of God, I ſtand by the Wiſdom and Power of God: Therefore as by Faith I ſtand, ſo by Faith I ſhall quit my ſelf like a Man, and make all that are Enemies to God and Man, throughout the whole World, to tremble, as the Devil and all the Workers of Evil, that are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged with him and for him, againſt the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion, and the Government of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which is for Unity, Peace and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, for Piety and Vertue, which would have all the Sons and the Daughters of Men ceaſe to do evil and learn to do well, and in every Grace and Vertue to excell; which is for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Proteſtant Religion, and the Peace and the Proſperity of all Kingdoms. Therefore all that call themſelves Chriſtians and Proteſtants in <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and do not conform to ſo excellent a Government, which is for Love and Vnion, to prevent Strife and Contention, Sedition and Treaſon, Wars and Confuſion; they be fooliſh, proud, ſtubborn, and rebellious Children; but they that will do
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40139:4"/>what they ſhould not do, muſt be made to do what they would not: For though Men are not to be compelled to be Religious, yet they are to be ſubdued when they Rebellious: By the Laws of the Land, by the Command of them that have Power in their hand, they ought to be made Servants and Labourers to them that do conform, that is, to bear moſt Burdens, to pay moſt Taxes, to furniſh our Royal and Gracious Sovereign with Men and Money, when he doth require it, and may have occaſion to uſe it. This will be the way for to bring home many that be gone a ſtay, and to reprove, rebuke, and to condemn them that will not obey; this will be the way for Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts to become Proteſtants, and for Proteſtants and Papiſts to become good Chriſtians and Loyal and Obedient Subjects. This will be the way for to prevent much Evil, that it may not come upon the Nations, to remove much Evil that is, come, and to procure and ſecure great Honour, Peace, and Proſperity, to our Royal King and many Kingdoms. This will be the way that we ſhall become as fair as the Moon, as clear as the Sun, and as terrible as an Army with Banners; ſo that we ſhall become a Wonder to our Selves, a Terror to our Enemies, and a Crown and a Glory to all Kings and Kingdoms. This will be the way for the workers of Evil to become workers of Righteouſneſs, ſo that Righteouſneſs will run down like a mighty ſtream, and the Wickedneſs of the Wicked will come to an end, to the great ſhame, contempt, and terror of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40139:4"/>Devil, who is the Author and Cauſe of all Evil, among the Sons of Men. He is that Prince of the Air, that is every where to make Strife and Contention, Sedition and Treaſon, Wars and Confuſion, among all Perſons, Families, Cities and Kingdoms: He ſets Learned Men one againſt another, to confound and deſtroy each other; he ſets the Wiſe againſt the Strong, the Strong againſt the Weak, and the Rich againſt the Poor, to bring Deſolation among all Perſons and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: He ſets the Turk againſt the Pope, and the Pope againſt him, and the French King a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them both; and is it not time for me to ſet my ſelf againſt them all, for their great ſhame and down fall; but I ſhall ſet my ſelf moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Devil, becauſe he hated Man from the beginning, and did endeavour to deſtroy him, as ſoon as he had a Being; he is a Murderer, he cauſed <hi>Cain</hi> to kill his Brother <hi>Abel,</hi> he has cauſed all Wars and Murders that have been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all Perſons, in all Nations, in all Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations; he is an implacable Enemy to the Sons and the Daughters of Men; he ſets the Church againſt the State, and the State againſt the Church, that ſo there may be neither Church nor State among them; but the Devil ſhall be deceived of his expectation, to his great ſhame and condemnation, for I ſhall ſet all Wiſe, Strong, Rich, and Learned Men againſt him; yea, all People in all Nations, that do love the Peace and the Proſperity of their Souls, and the Comfort of their Lives; therefore I ſhall ſet the Turk and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40139:5"/>the Pope, and the French King againſt him, and all that do aſſiſt him and them, becauſe he has deceived them with a Religion that tends to their ſhame, and will be to their ruin, if they do not leave it in due time. Therefore all that have a Soul to ſave, I hope will leave that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which makes them the Devils Slaves. He that winneth Souls from the love of the things of this World, and from the ſervice of the Devil, the God of this World, that Man is Wiſe, and Stronger than the Devil; he is Wiſe for himſelf and he is Wiſe for others, that the Sons and the Daughters of Men may enjoy the greateſt freedom, the freedom of the Mind; the greateſt Liberty, the Liberty of the Will; and the greateſt Power, Power againſt Sin; and the greateſt Victory, Victory over the World. I am at War for them with the Devil, who is the God of this World, who doth do what he can with the things of this World, to deceive the Sons and the Daughters of Men, to win their Souls from them; but before the Devil ſhall have his will over the Sons of Men, he ſhall be chained and confined to his Den, and there will I make him ſhake and quake, by the Power of Faith and the Word of God, which is an Iron Rod, and a ſharp Sword, by which I ſhall ſmite him and wound him home; I ſhall not fear him nor ſpare him, but play and diſplay upon him Hail-ſtones and Coles of Fire, by the power of Faith and the Word of Gods Power.</p>
            <p>Sir, It was long before I did begin to make
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40139:5"/>War with the Devil, but having begun to make War with him in my own Perſon, for the great Joy, Peace and Proſperity of all Nations; I ſhall not leave him, but will vex and perplex him, wound and confound him, till all Strife, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and Wars, throughout the whole World doth ceaſe, and among all People in all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, there be a free Trade, great Joy, and a laſting Peace; that the Sons of Men may live Conquerors in the World, and die Conquerors over Sin, Death, Hell, and the Devil. They muſt hate what is Evil, what is Evil in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, for it is weakneſs and fooliſhneſs to ſpeak gainſt Evil in others, and to love and approve of it in themſelves; but they that hate what is Evil in themſelves, will begin to loath it, and then to leave it, and then to be weary of it; and then the Devil will be weary of them. This is the way for the Workers of Evil to leave the Devil, and the Devil to leave them.</p>
            <p>This is my great Deſign, and the labour and travel of my Mind, for the Devil to leave the Sons of Men, and the Sons of Men to leave him, that ſo he may take up his reſt in his Den, and not for to have any lodging among them; but in his Den there let him roar, rage, and ſwell, but no more cauſe the Sons of Men for to rebel. They that do hate what is Evil in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and do love what is Good in others, will labour to be good in their own Perſons, and to do much good in their Generation, for the great honour of God, the King, and the Nation.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:40139:6"/>
            <p>They that would overcome the Devil, who is the author and cauſe of all Evil, they muſt not ſlight and undervalue the Publick Prayers of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> becauſe they be ſuitable and ſeaſonable, profitable and comfortable, for all Perſons in all Nations, for to inform them and to reform them, if they be not wanting to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; they be ſuch Prayers, that will teach Men to know how to Pray in their Families, and between God and their own Souls, from whom they may have what they can deſire, as truth of Grace, ſtrength of Grace, and increaſe of Grace.</p>
            <p>The Prayer of the Upright it is Gods Delight, and tends to Mans great Peace, Profit and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; it is Faith, Prayer and Meditation, that will drive the Devil from Mens Habitations, ſo that they will enjoy great Conſolation, and be free from Condemnation and everlaſting Damnation. Prayer without Faith it is heartleſs, and Faith without Prayer it is fruitleſs; Faith and Prayer will purifie the fouleſt heart, that the Devil can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not lodge there in any part; they will ſtrengthen the weakeſt Memory, and comfort the ſaddeſt Spirit. Faith and Prayer will make a weak Man ſtrong in the Power of God, as bold as a Lion, for the great Honour of God and the King, and Wiſer than the Devil and all the workers of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, who are Enemies unto him. Therefore what Victory or Conqueſt any of the Sons of Men do get by the Power of Faith, over Sin, Death, Hell, and the Devil, and over the workers of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40139:6"/>Evil, the Glory of it is to be given to the God of Heaven, and the Honour and the Profit of it to the King of that Nation, who is over that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>Well might I declare in due time, for the great Joy, Peace and Proſperity of Mankind, that our Royal Sovereign <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> would be the Chiefeſt and moſt Renowned Emperor in the World, and over the World, becauſe I have been at War for him with the Devil, who is the God of this World; but I have not been at War with him with an Army of Men, but by the Power of Faith I have him under my feet, and ſhall tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over him, for the Glory and the great Glory of the moſt High, and the great Honour and Exaltation of <hi>Englands</hi> Royal Majeſty among the Sons of Men, and above any of them; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all Heathen and Popiſh Kings, Prieſts, Princes and Emperors in the World, for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Renown of the Proteſtant Religion, and the Government of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and and for the Peace and Proſperity of all King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</p>
            <p>Sir, it has been a Sin and a great Sin, of too many, both in Church and State, both Learned and Unlearned Men, that they have not proved and improved their Wiſdom, their Knowledge, their Power, and their Courage, for the Honour of our Royal Sovereign <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, King of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> as they might have done, but they have too
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40139:7"/>much improved it againſt him and his Royal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, our late Royal and Gracious Soveraign; a King too wiſe, mild, and too good, for a proud, ſtubborn, and rebellious Generation; but the right hand of the Lord will find out all his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, both at home and abroad. Let the Wiſe, Godly, and the Learned, of the Church of Chriſt, in <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> yea of his Church throughout the whole World, conſider if it be not time for the Lord of Hoſts to make bare his Arm, and to make a Man ſtrong for himſelf and our Royal Soveraign, <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> when that too many have made themſelves ſtrong in Parties againſt him, to undermine and overthrow the Proteſtant Religion, and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> but what will they get but Shame and Confuſion, for they will be brought down, and that with a Witneſs, and that without having a Sword in my hand, or Men or Money at command; it will be known in this day of Gods Power, whoſe word ſhall ſtand, the word of God or the word of Man: I ſay the word of God that will prevail, and all that truſt to this Party or that Opinion, to Carnal Wiſdom, Power and Strength, their Hearts will fail: Therefore let all that handle the Sword, or draw out the Sword, to undermine and overthrow the Proteſtant Religion, the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and our Royal So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> under pretence of a better Governour, a better Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verment,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40139:7"/>and a better Religion, let them periſh like <hi>Siſera</hi> and <hi>Jabin,</hi> like <hi>Pharaoh, Saul,</hi> and proud <hi>Haman,</hi> who became as Dung upon the face of the Earth; but let them that love the Lord and delight to honour the King, our Royal and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Soveraign, his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain;</hi> Let them be like the Sun that goes forth in his might, that may give a greater and a better Light; a Light that may ſhine ſo clear, as may Revive, Refreſh, Counſel, Comfort and Streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Fellow Members, Fellow Labourers, Fellow Travellers, and Fellow Soldiers, and Fellow Citizens in the Wilderneſs of this World, far and near.</p>
            <p>The way of the Wicked it is as Darkneſs, they know not at what they ſtumble, but the path of the Juſt it is as the ſhining Light, that ſhines brighter and brighter, till it comes to the perfect day. The Lord is my Light and Salvation, whom ſhall I fear? Not the Devil nor the workers of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. The Lord is my Light and Salvation, my ſtrong Tower, and moſt Royal Habitation; whom ſhall I not make to fear? Them that will not love and fear the God of Heaven, and honour our Royal and Gracious Sovereign, <hi>Charles</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, King of <hi>Great Britain.</hi> Whom ſhall I not make to fear in this day of Gods Power, by the power of his Spirit, and the word of his Power? Will it not be the Devil, and all the workers of Evil, all that be engaged with him and for him, againſt the Proteſtant Religion, the Government of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the Perſon of our
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40139:8"/>Royal Soveraign, his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain?</hi> Will it not be all they that be for Strife and Contention, Sedition and Treaſon, for Wars and Confuſion; all that make Religion a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Diſcourſe to no purpoſe; all that have a name to live and are dead, all that call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Saints and are Devils incarnate? Will it not be all Self-ſekers and Men-pleaſers, lovers of themſelves more than lovers of God, their King and Countrey? It is weakneſs and fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, if not madneſs, for to make a noiſe about Religion, for this Party and that Opinion, and do not labour to get power againſt Sin, and victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry over the Devil. This is the way for to make <hi>Rome</hi> to ſhake, and <hi>Spain</hi> to quake, and all that are Enemies to the Government of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> their Hearts to ake, more than many Armies of Men. This is the way for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of Sin, Satan, and Antichriſt, for to grow weaker and weaker, and the Kingdoms of our Lord and Saviour ſtronger and ſtronger; ſo that the whole Earth will be filled with the Knowledge and the Glory of the Lord, as the VVaters cover the Sea; ſo that the People in moſt Nations will praiſe God, yea, all will learn to praiſe him with new Obedience, becauſe they have their Being from him, and their well Being is in him. This is the way for the Throne of our Royal Soveraign to be eſtabliſhed in Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſo that the Workers of Iniquity, the Seed of Evil Doers, the Children of Diſobedience, who are for Strife and Contention, Sedition and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40139:8"/>Treaſon, for Wars and Confuſion, will be affraid and aſhamed to come into his Majeſties Royal Preſence, ſo that his Majeſties Royal Court will be the moſt Renowned'ſt Court under the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, for Vnity, Peace, and Concord, for Piety and Vertue, for Wiſdom, Power, and Strength; for Honours, Riches, and great Glory. So that we ſhall ſoon become the Wonder and the Glory of the World, the Crown of Kingdoms, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and the Delight of Nations, the Joy of the whole Earth, and the City of the great King: So that moſt People in all Nations, will be in love with the Proteſtant Religion, and all Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and Popiſh Kings, Prieſts, Princes, and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors in the World, will be aſhamed of their Religion, and will be ready and willing for to ſerve and to honour our Royal and Gracious Soveraign <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> as the Chief Soveraign among the Sons of Men, for Wiſdom, Power, and Strength over them; and well they may, becauſe the Lord of Hoſts is with him as a Mighty Man, as a Man of War, to ſubdue his Enemies under his Feet, and as a God of Peace, to cauſe all Strife, Contention, and Wars, throughout the whole World to ceaſe: Therefore let not any Deſpiſe the day of ſmall things, but when and by whom the Lord of Hoſts doth make bare his Arm, let all Fleſh be ſilent, as it doth become them; for though the Lord be ſlow to Anger, yet is he great in Power, who can with his Right Hand and Holy Arm, with one Man, make all his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40139:9"/>throughout the whole World to tremble. The time is come, that he will have Inquiſition made for the Blood of his Son, Holy Prophets, Apoſtles, Martyrs; and for the Life of our late Royal, and Gracious Soveraign: All theſe have been put to Death by unreaſonable, bloody, and deceitful Men. But what will they do in the day of Viſitation, and where will they fly for help? There is no flying from the power of that Man by Sea or Land, in whom the Lord of Hoſts doth make bare his Arm, for his Arm is very long and very ſtrong, and that his Enemies will know to their great ſhame and overthrow, that be Enemies to the Proteſtant Religion, and to the Government of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Who knows the Wiſdom, the Power, and the Strength of that Man, that is ſtrong in the Lord, and in the Power of his Might? What can he not do? What may he not do in his own Perſon to ſerve his Generation, for the Peace and Proſperity of many Nations? Therefore not unto Man, not unto Man, but let all the Glory be given to the moſt High, from Men and Angels, and that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually, for his great Wiſdom, Power, Glory, and Majeſty: And great Honour and Renown, great Joy, Peace and Proſperity, from the moſt High, upon <hi>Englands</hi> Royal Majeſty, upon his Royal Perſon, and all his Royal Relations, that ſo he and they may long live to Reign for God and with God, among the Sons of Men, from Generation to Generation, for the great Joy, Peace and Proſperity of all Nations.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:40139:9"/>
            <p>What Victory or Conqueſt is got by any one Perſon, or by an Army of Men, the Glory of it is to be given to the God of Heaven, and the Honour of it to the King of that Nation. When <hi>David</hi> in his own Perſon did get the Victory and Conqueſt over <hi>Goliah,</hi> the Philiſtins Champion, it was a Honour and a great Honour to King <hi>Saul</hi> and all <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And when <hi>Joab</hi> with King <hi>Davids</hi> Men did get the Victory over the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren oſ <hi>Ammon,</hi> and had taken their Royal City the City of Waters, <hi>Joab</hi> he ſends for his Lord King <hi>David,</hi> to come and to take the Honour and the Crown, and the Glory of it, which was due to him. Therefore what ever Wiſdom, Power, Courage, or any Grace, any Subject in <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> hath received from the God of all Wiſdom, Power and Grace, it doth become them ſo to prove and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them, that they may tend for the Glory of the moſt High, and the great Honour and Renown of <hi>Englands</hi> Royal Majeſty. Kings are born for Honour and great Honour in this World, therefore it is the Duty of Loyal and Faithful Subjects, to do what they can to uphold their Honour; to maintain it, and to increaſe it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Sons of Men, and above any of them, and not in the leaſt to oppoſe them and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throne them, as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> has done too many.</p>
            <p>There is a Generation of Men that are not for Kingly Government over them, but they would have a King among themſelves; ſuch another
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40139:10"/>Tyrant as <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> was; theſe are they that make a noiſe about Religion, of Chriſts Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Reign 'upon Earth; but theſe will be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of their Expectation, to their great Shame and Condemnation. The Reign of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, it is Spiritual and not Temporal; when he was upon Earth he made himſelf of no Reputation, but took upon him the form of a Servant; therefore the Jews did flight and undervalue him: ſo that he has no encouragement to come in his own Perſon among the Sons of Men, but he will come to Judge the World, and to Condemn them moſt that would have him come to Reign among them, and will not let him Reign in their Hearts, and to rule and over-rule them by his Word and Spirit. The Kingdom of Chriſt, it is not in outward Glory, but it is in Righteouſneſs, Joy and Peace in the Heart: It is Righteouſneſs that will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt a Perſon, be he High or Low, Rich or Poor, Learned or Unlearned, with an Ornament of Grace and a Crown of Glory, which the Devil nor the World cannot give nor take away; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the Houſe of the Righteous there is the richeſt Treaſure and the ſweeteſt Pleaſure, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is a ſound Heart, which is the life of the Fleſh.</p>
            <p>A wholeſome Tongue, which is a Tree of Life, and Righteous Lips, which are the delight of Kings, yea, of him who is King of Kings, and the onely Ruler and beſt Ruler of Princes, becauſe he is the Prince of Peace, the Lord of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40139:10"/>Hoſts, who doth what he will among the Sons of Men, both with the Government and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them, becauſe he has all Power in his own hand, and the whole Creation at command.</p>
            <p>As the Lord of Hoſts is the Prince of Peace, ſo he is the Son of Righteouſneſs, who loveth the Righteous, and doth preſerve them, and layeth up ſound Wiſdom for the Righteous: He lays it up for them, that they may lay it out for him in due time and ſeaſon, to prevent much Evil, that it may not come to a City or a Kingdom to remove much Evil that is come, and to procure and ſecure great Honour, Peace, and Proſperity to King and Kingdom: By him and for him it is that Kings do Reign, and in the World remain; he ſets them up and keeps them up, for his own Will and Pleaſure; they are not ſet up for the will and pleaſure of Men, neither have they any power for to oppoſe and depoſe them, as too many have done, to the great ſhame and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their own Faces, and much Trouble and Miſery of too many Nations; but the Righteous Lord, who is a great God and mighty King over all the Earth, has known the Soul of our Royal So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign in great Adverſity; he has been his Strength in time of Trouble, he has brought him out of great Tribulation, and will bring him to great Honour and Exaltation, for the Glory of his great Name, for the Honour of his Holy Goſpel, and the Government of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the Peace and Proſperity of all Kingdoms, to the ſhame of them
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40139:11"/>that are Enemies to the Proteſtant Religion, and to the Government of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, To lay a Foundation for ſome ſtately Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation, for a Church, a Temple, or ſome great Hall for Publick Uſe and Service, it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, and many will countenance, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and ſet forward, a Work of that nature, and they do well; but to lay a Foundation by Divine Meditation, for the great Honour and Exaltation of a Kings Perſon, and the great Joy, Peace, and Proſperity of many Nations, it is more Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, and at this time ſuitable and ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, profitable and comfortable, and advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious tomany Perſons, Families, Cities and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms: therefore all that do love the peace and the proſperity of their Souls, and the comfort of their Lives, ſhould countenance, encourage, and ſet forward this high and honourable Work, that is for the Glory, and the great Glory of the moſt High, and the great Honour and Exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Englands</hi> Royal Majeſty, our Royal and Gracious Sovereign <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> among the Sons of Men, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove any of them; above all Heathen and Popiſh Kings, Prieſts, Princes, and Emperors in the World; that ſo all Nations may be freed from Slavery, and throughout the whole World great Joy, Peace and Proſperity; ſo that in theſe days of the Goſpel will the Righteous flouriſh, and in the Reign of our Royal Sovereign there will be abundance of Peace, from the Wiſdom and the Power of the Prince of Peace; who can when
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40139:11"/>he pleaſe, and with whom he pleaſe, cauſe all Strife, Contention and Wars throughout the whole World to ceaſe; to the great Shame, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and Terror of all them that be for Strife and Contention, Sedition and Treaſon, for Wars and Confuſion. Shall the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> mind and regard her Children that be workers of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil? Shall ſhe countenance and encourage them in that which is ſinful? Shall ſhe give them great Gifts, and promiſe them great Rewards to make Strife and Contention, Sedition and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Wars and Confuſion, to undermine and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow the Proteſtant Religion, the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and our Royal Sovereign his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain?</hi> And ſhall not that Man be minded and regarded, by the Wiſe, Godly, and the Learned of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that ſhall deny himſelf, overcome himſelf, and lay out himſelf, to undermine and confound the Devil, and all the Workers of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil; all that are Enemies to the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and to the Goverment of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> but the work of Faith and the labour of Love is regarded by the God of Love, though it may be ſlighted and undervalued by too many of the Sons of Men: But what our Saviour ſaid, that ſhall I ſay, <hi>They that be not his Friends are his Enemies; they that be not for him are againſt him:</hi> Who can with one Man wound and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found all his Enemies, by Sea and by Land. Therefore they that do not countenance, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage, and ſet forward this noble Deſign, that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40139:12"/>he has enabled me to make known in time, for the great Joy, Peace and Proſperity of Mankind; they be not Friends but Enemies to the Peace and Proſperity of their own Souls and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of their Lives.</p>
            <p>Sir, He that handleth a Matter wiſely ſhall find Good, and who ſo truſteth in the Lord happy is he. As my Faith is from the God of my Hope, ſo my Hope is in the God of my Faith, who will bring forth the Righteouſneſs of his Servant as the Light, and his Judgment as the Noon-day, to make good what he has enabled him to hold forth in this Generation, for the great Joy, Peace and Proſperity of all Nations; to that end I have declared that our Royal Sovereign <hi>Charles</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> in this Generation will be the Chiefeſt and the moſt Renowned'ſt Emperor in the World and over the World; the time is come, that it is to be made known to all People, in all Nations, that it is already done, and ſo well done, that it is not all the Powers of Hell, nor all the Powers of the World, that can undo it again: It is done, but not by the Counſel of Men in Parliament, nor out of Parliament; it is done, but not by Strife and Contention, Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Treaſon, by Wars and Confuſion; but it is done by a ſecret Decree from the God of Peace, that ſo all Strife, Contention and Wars, throughout the whole World may ceaſe; that ſo among all People in all Nations there may be a free Trade, great Joy, and a laſting Peace. This Noble and Royal Decree from the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40139:12"/>God of Peace, it is his ſecret Determination, for to diſappoint in due time the Turk, the Pope, and the French King, of their Expectation, that they ſhall not Rule and Over-rule the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as too long they have done, for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and their own Luſts; but the God of Peace, who is the God of Power, will have his Annointed, and our Royal Sovereign <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> to Rule and to Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule them and all Nations, by the Word of his Power, which is the Scepter of his Grace, by which he will be known in all Paths and Places of the World , to be the Creator of Heaven, the Earth, and the Sea.</p>
            <p>Sir, As our Royal Sovereign has this great Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to be the Chiefeſt and moſt Renowned Emperor in the World and over the World, from Gods Royal Decree and Determination, to Rule and Over-rule the Nations for him and with him, by the word of his Power; ſo he has this great Honour by way of Conqueſt, but not by the power of the Sword, but by the power of Faith, between God and my own Soul, over the Devil, the God of this World, who has deceived and deſtroyed too many hundred thouſands of Perſons in all Nations, with the things of this World that be uncertain and deceitful. They be like a Bladder, full of Wind, but do not ſatisfie the Mind: But the time is come, that the Devil that has deceived too many in all Nations, I ſhall endeavour to deceive him very much in this Generation, but not Sir of Silver or of Gold,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40139:13"/>of Houſes or of Lands, but of as many Souls as I can; becauſe the Soul of one Man or Woman more worth than all the Kingdoms of this World.</p>
            <p>Sir, The Soul of a Man is capable of higher Enjoyments and greater Honours than this World can afford; for all things under the Sun is but vanity: Honours are uncertain, Riches are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful, and the Pleaſures of this World they be more bitter than ſweet; they fill many with Pain, ſome with Shame, and ſome with a foul and loathſome Diſeaſe; but they give the Soul no true Eaſe: but they that hunger and thirſt after Righteouſneſs, will be filled with Grace and enjoy much peace, that peace which the World cannot give nor take away; but there is no peace to the Wicked, to the Workers of Iniquity, what-ever they do, where-ever they go, till they come to be Workers and Lovers of Righteouſneſs, then they will have peace with God and Joy in God.</p>
            <p>The work of Righteouſneſs is peace, and the effect of Righteouſneſs is Quietneſs to the Mind, and will prove profitable to Mankind. The La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of the Righteous tendeth to Life, to the Life and Comfort of his own Soul, and of the Souls of many in Court, City and Countrey.</p>
            <p>The Devil, who is the God of this World, doth labour to do what he can with the things of this World, to deceive the Sons and the Daughters of Men, to win the Souls of them. But Sir, He that can win Souls from the Devil, and the love of this preſent Evil World, he is Wiſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40139:13"/>for God and Strong in God, and will be fully and greatly Rewarded by God: For as the Fruit of the Righteous is a Tree of Life, ſo the Reward of the Righteous, is a Crown of Life, which the Righteous Lord will give to every one that is a lover and a worker of Righteouſneſs. The Secret of the Lord, Sir, is with the Righteous; what he will have brought about for the great Honour and Exaltation of a Kings Perſon, and the great Joy, Peace and Proſperity of a Nation; and it is not all the powers of Hell, nor all the powers of the World that can hinder it. There is a time and a ſeaſon for every purpoſe under the Sun, much more for Gods ſecret Decrees to be made known and done: For what the moſt Wiſe God doth Will, before time, he will have it brought about and fulfilled in due time, by that man whom he doth give wiſdom and power to underſtand his mind: for the Will of God is the Maſter-wheel that ſets a work all the powers in man, and all the powers of man, to bring about what he knows that is beſt to be done, for the great honour, the peace and the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of a King and many Kingdoms. There be many devices in the heart of man, but the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of the Lord that ſhall ſtand, and the thoughts of his heart in all generations; what he will have brought about among all Perſons in all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to the great ſhame, contempt and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of the Devil, and all the workers of Evil, who are for Strife and Contention, Sedition and Treaſon, for Wars and Confuſion: But Sir, the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40139:14"/>God of Peace knows when, how, and by whom he pleaſeth, for to cauſe all Strife, Contention and Wars throughout the whole World to ceaſe; and among all People in all Nations, a free Trade, great Joy, and a laſting Peace: to that end this great Lord has enabled me to underſtand his Mind, and to make it known in due time. They that muſt wait Sir upon the Lord, muſt be of good Courage, and then he will ſtrengthen their Hearts, that they ſhall be able to act for him, and to act with him, in high and honourable Work It is God that has made my Feet like Hinds Feet, to leap over a Wall of difficulty and danger: He has girded me with Strength, and has made my way plain, and will make his work proſperous that he has wrought in me in this day of his power, by the power of his Spirit, which is a Spirit of Light and of Life, of Liberty and of Ability, for to enable them that do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy it, and will be ruled by it, for to attain, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, maintain, and proclaim, that which is ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſeaſonable, profitable, comfortable and advantagious for all perſons in all Nations, that do love the peace and the proſperity of their Souls, and the comfort of their Lives. But Sir, There is a Generation of Men that will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve no more than they can by their Senſe and Reaſon underſtand, and ſuch Men be always at a ſtand, for the good of a City and a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to bring Order out of Confuſion, Light out of Darkneſs, Good out of Evil, and Peace out of Trouble: but to him that believes and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40139:14"/>knows he believes, all things is poſſible to be done, that is lawful, commendable and moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable under the Sun; what is lovely and praiſe worthy among the Sons of Men, for the peace and proſperity of them. Is is but reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for all Men to believe in the Lord of Life, who is the King of Glory and the Prince of Peace; but to Believe in him and to Act for him, it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Reaſon but not againſt Reaſon: it is the work of Faith and the labour of Love that can do it. Sir, A Friend loveth at all times, and a Brother is born for Adverſity; for a Nation, yea, for many Nations, great Joy, Peace and Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which will be brought about in this Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, for <hi>Englands</hi> great Honour and Exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and for her Enemies great Shame and Condemnation. Therefore cry out and ſhout thou Inhabitant of <hi>Sion,</hi> thou Church of Chriſt, in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> yea, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole World: for great is the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the mid'ſt of thee, for to make thee moſt Renowned among the Sons of Men, for Wildom, Power, and Strength over them; over all Heathen and Popiſh Kings, Prieſts, Princes and Emperors in the World, over all the workers of Imquity, the Seed of Evil Doers, and the Children of Diſobedience; over all that are Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to the Goſpel, to the Proteſtant Religion, and to the Goverment of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and that without making of War or ſhedding of Blood: This is the Lords doings, who is great in Counſel and mighty in Power, to work in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40139:15"/>Man, with Man, and for Man, when Parliaments, Armies and Counſels may be at a ſtand.</p>
            <p>Sir, It is the unbelief of Men that doth hinder the God of Heaven from working in them and with them, for the good of themſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. There is nothing too hard for the God of Heaven, who is the God of all Wiſdom and Power, for to bring about by that Man that doth Believe in him, and can act his Faith for him: For though Faith be Gods Gift, yet Man muſt Act his Faith, that will bring Glory to God, Honour and Renown to a Kings Perſon, and Peace and Proſperity to a Nation.</p>
            <p>Sir, The Lord Reigneth who made the World, and doth Govern the World as one Man, and can do it with one Man, when and by whom he pleaſe to make bare his Arm; and that his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies will know to their great ſhame and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw. For this great Lord and King will make quick and powerful Work in this Generation, for the Information, Reformation, and Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of many Nations in this day of his Power, by his Word and Spirit of Power; that ſo the Heathens may be Converted; and Jews and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles brought into one fold; that ſo all Strife, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and Wars throughout the whole World may ceaſe, and among all People in all Nations, a free Trade, great Joy, and a laſting Peace. So that Sir, it is in vain for the Turk to ſtrive to be greater than the Pope, or the Pope greater than he, or the French King greater than them; our Royal and Gracious Sovereign <hi>Charles</hi> the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40139:15"/>Second King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> is Wiſer and Stronger, and Greater than them all; but not by the Wiſdom and Power of Men, not by the Sword of them, but by the Wiſdom and Power of God in Man, with Man and for Man; that ſo all Nations may be freed from Slavery, and through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole World, great Joy, Peace and Proſperity, to the great Shame, Contempt and Terror of the Devil, and all the Workers of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil.</p>
            <p>Sir, Shall the God of all Wiſdom and Power enable me to work with him and to work for him, in ſuch High and Honourable Work, Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, Glorious, and Crowning Work; and ſhall not my Perſon be minded and regarded by the Wiſe, Godly, and the Learned of the Church of Chriſt, in <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> yea, throughout the whole World. Am I not a Member of the Church of Chriſt in <hi>England,</hi> and a Member of the City of <hi>London?</hi> Am I not a Subject to our Royal and Gracious Sovereign <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Great Britain?</hi> What though I am by Birth, Education, and Trade, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior to many, and by Nature as bad as any, yet he that is Mighty and moſt Mighty among the Sons of Men, and over the Angels in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, who has put down many Proud and Mighty Angels and Men from their Seat, and has exalted among the Sons of Men many that have been Humble and Meek; this great Lord and King, who doth Try and will Judge the Children of Men, has magnified me among many of them;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40139:16"/>but it is with thoſe Graces that makes me ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in his own Eyes, and ſerviceable for his Glory. Therefore not unto Man, not unto Man, no, nor to the Angels in Heaven, but let all the Glory be given to the God of Heaven, for his great Wiſdom, Power, Glory and Majeſty, who can do what he will, and work with whom he will among the Sons of Men, to manifeſt his Wiſdom and Power over the Devil, and all the Workers of Evil.</p>
            <p>Sir, Men are to be minded and regarded, be they High or Low, Rich or Poor, for their Wiſdom and their Learning, for their Power and their Strength; for their Honours and their Riches; for their great and high Places; but moſt of all for their rich Graces, for their Faith, that works by Love, becauſe it is a wonder-working Grace, for the God of Heaven, and a Victorious and a Glorious Grace among the Sons of Men, for the great Joy, Peace and Proſperity of them.</p>
            <p>Sir, I hope that the Wiſe, Godly, and the Learned of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> will not be offended, that I can manifeſt the power of Faith, for the Glory and the great Glory of the moſt High, and the great Honour and Exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Englands</hi> Royal Majeſty, of his Royal Perſon, and of all his Royal Relations; which will be for the great Joy, Peace and Proſperity of all Nitions: To that end let all that can pray, Pray for the long Life and proſperous Reign of our Royal Sovereign <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, King
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40139:16"/>of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and of all his Royal Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that ſo he and they may long live to Reign for God and with God, among the Sons of Men, from Generation to Generation, and at laſt for ever with Holy Angels and Men in his Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
            <p>Sir, It is in vain for the Miniſters of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel in <hi>London</hi> and about <hi>London,</hi> to preach the Word of God in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, if they do not mind, and regard, countenance and encourage that Man who hath believed their Report, and to whom the Arm of the Lord is revealed. What have they to mind? Who ſhould they mind more than ſuch a Man who can ſet to his Seal that God and his Word is true, and their Doctrine ſo far as they agree thereto? Has not their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and their Miniſtry for a long time been ſlighted and undervalued by them who are E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to the Proteſtant Religion, and to the Government of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that for a long time have made Religion a buſineſs of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to no purpoſe? But Sir, It will be known to the great Joy and Shame of many a one, that Religion is a Buſineſs of the higheſt Nature and the greateſt Conqueſt; and that, not by the power of the Sword but by the power of Faith, and the Word of God; which will prevail when all the Traditions and Additions of Men will fail. As a Vertuous Woman, Sir, is a Crown to her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and the Glory of the Man, ſo a Wiſe, Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, Vallorous, and a Couragious Man, is a Crown and a Glory to all the Miniſters of the Goſpel in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40139:17"/>the Land; yea, he is a Crown and a Glory to the God of Heaven: He is a Crown and a Glory to a King and a Kingdom; ſuch a Man is a wonder to himſelf, and will prove a Terror to the Devil, and to the Workers of Evil, who are Engaged with him and for him, againſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, and the Goverment of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and that without having a Sword in his hand, or Men or Money at command.</p>
            <p>Sir, This is from the power of Faith, which is the power of God in Man, and with Man, and for Man; and will make all that are Enemies to God and Man throughout the whole World to tremble. Let not any therefore ſlight and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalue a ſpark of Faith in themſelves, or in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; but let every one labour to get it, to keep it, to prove and improve it; becauſe it is ſuch a Spark, that in whom it is wrought, it will in due time break forth into a Flame, and put the Devil and all the Workers of Evil to ſhame, and bring a King and a Kingdom to greater Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Renown, and Fame, than has yet been done, by all the Parliaments, Armies, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, that have been ſince <hi>England</hi> has enjoyed a King.</p>
            <p>Sir, It was by Faith, that I did underſtand that our Royal Soveraign <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> would be the Chiefeſt and moſt Renowned Emperor in the World, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Sons of Men, for Wiſdom, Power and Strength over them; over all Heathen and Popiſh Kings, Prieſts, Princes, and Emperors in the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40139:17"/>World. Therefore I was not affraid nor aſhamed to make it known in due time, for the great Joy, Peace, and Proſperity of Mankind, that ſo the times may be better than they have been in this Generation, and many the better for them in all Nations. This is the way that we ſhall ſoon, Sir, become the Wonder and the Glory of the World, the Crown of Kingdoms, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and the Delight of Nations, the Joy of the whole Earth, and the City of the Great King; for Unity, Peace, and Concord; for Piety and Vertue; for Wiſdom, Power and Strength; for Honours, Riches, and great Glory: Therefore let the people praiſe God, yea, let all Heathen and popiſh Kings, Prieſts, Princes and Emperors in the World praiſe him, and give unto him the Glory due to his Name; who can do what he will, and work with whom he will among the Sons Men, to manifeſt his wiſdom and power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them; that ſo all Strife, Contention and Wars throughout the whole World may ceaſe, and among all people in all Nations, a free Trade, great Joy, and a laſting peace. Therefore it will be Rebellion for any perſons in any Nation for to make War againſt the Proteſtants or the Proteſtant Religion, the Government of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or our Royal Soveraign his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> whom the God of peace did bring to his Throne in Peace in a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful manner, beyond the Expectation of the Wiſeſt and the Learned'ſt in the Nation. And as the Lord, who is the moſt Wiſe and moſt Strong,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40139:18"/>Sir, has done great things for the Preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Reſtauration of our Royal Sovereign; ſo he will do great things in this Generation, for his great Honour and Exaltation, for his great Joy and Conſolation; becauſe he is a Prince for Peace, and a lover of Peace; and becauſe his Subjects do enjoy the greateſt Liberty, and are Men of the greateſt Wiſdom, Courage, and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility. So that Sir, all People in all Nations will come to know and to underſtand what a great and mighty King our Royal and Gracious Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> is, among the Sons of Men, for Wiſdom, Power, and Strength over them; who can with one of his Subjects bid Defiance to the Turk, the Pope, and the Devil, and all the Workers of Evil, to their greater Shame, Contempt and Terror, than an Army of Ten hundred thouſand Men can; becauſe the Lord of Hoſts is with him as a mighty Man, as a Man of War, to ſubdue his Enemies under his Feet; and as a God of Peace, to cauſe all Strife, Contention and Wars throughout the whole World to ceaſe, to the great Shame of all them that be for Strife and Contention, Sedition and Treaſon, for Wars and Confuſion. Therefore let the Righteous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce and be glad, for Light is ſown for the Righteous, and Gladneſs, Sir for the Vpright in Heart; for in the Reign of our Royal Sovereign will the Righteous flouriſh, and in his days there will be abundance of Peace, from the Wiſdom and the Power of the God of Peace.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40139:18"/>So that Sir, The Devil, the Author and the Cauſe of all Evil among the Sons of Men, will be aſhamed and confounded, becauſe he ſhall not do what he would do, to make Strife and Contention, Sedition and Treaſon, Wars and Confuſion among the Sons of Men, to the Ruin of them; but for all the Devils Fury, Rage and Madneſs againſt the Sons and Daughters of Men, the Righteous will live and die in Peace, to the Terror of him.</p>
            <p>Sir, The Devil knows that I hate him, and will ſet the whole World againſt him; for he has made too many Fools of Quakers among the Sons of Men: And is it not time for me to make him ſhake and tremble in his Den, but not by the power of Men, but by the power of Faith, which is the power of the God of Heaven. I ſhall not fear him nor ſpare him, for he ſhall have no Reſt nor Quietneſs among the Sons of Men, as long as I have a Being among them.</p>
            <p>Sir, As an Ointment and Perfume doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce the Heart, ſo doth the Sweetneſs of a Man's Friend by hearty Counſel. It is good Counſel for all the Sons and Daughters of Men for to hate what is Evil, and then they will be free from the power and Dominion of the Devil.</p>
            <p>Would the Sons and the Daughters of Men be Wiſe, Strong, Rich, and Honourable in the Sight of God and Holy Angels; then they muſt not be affraid nor aſhamed to be Righteous, and to love Righteouſneſs: For it is Righteouſneſs, and only Righteouſneſs Sir, that will Exalt a Perſon,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40139:19"/>be he High or Low, Rich or Poor, Learned or Unlearned, with an Ornament of Grace and a Crown of Glory, which the Devil nor the World cannot give nor take away: But it is not the Righteouſneſs of Saints, or the Righteouſneſs of Angels that will Exalt a Perſon; but it is the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Every one by Faith muſt put him on for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and upon himſelf, as a Garment, as an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament, as a Royal Robe, as a Breaſt-plate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Fiery Darts of the Devil. They muſt put him on as a Helmet of Salvation, and as a Crown of Glory. They that by Faith put him on, muſt never put him off; but muſt own and make their Boaſt of him, more than the Men of the World can do of their Silver and Gold, of their Houſes and Lands, of their Offices and great Places; becauſe they be not ſatisfying, abiding, nor long laſting.</p>
            <p>But Sir, They that be clothed with the Sun of Righteouſneſs, have that which is abiding, ſatisfying, laſting, and everlaſting; Peace ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, and everlaſting Joy; and all the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and Pleaſures that the Mind and the Soul of Man is capable to enjoy. He is the Bread of Life, the Water of Life, the Fountain of Life, and the Souls Spring-Garden for Pleaſures and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light. All the Delights and Pleaſures that be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all the Sons of Men, and all the Angels in Heaven, are Ten thouſand times more in Chriſt; for in him is all Fulneſs and all Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; the richeſt Treaſures, and the ſweeteſt Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40139:19"/>Happy be they that do know their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in him, and thrice happy be they that do make an Improvement of him; becauſe Sir, the Merchandize of him is better than the Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize of Silver, and the Gain that comes from him is better than that of Fine Gold; he is more precious than Rubies, and all the things Men can deſire is not to be compared unto him. Length of days, Sir, is in his Right Hand, and in his Left Hand Riches and Honour; yea, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Riches and Honour. They that do love him will inherit Subſtance, that will for ever laſt and flouriſh; but they that do not love and delight in him, will enjoy only Shadows that will ſoon waſte and periſh; but the Lord of Life is a Tree of Life, for the Souls Pleaſure and Delight, and that not only for a day, but for every day: All the Souls freſh Springs of Joy, Peace and Comfort, is in him and from him. Therefore, Sir, happy be they that do lay hold upon him, and ſo is every one that doth retain him into the Heart of Love; becauſe he is altogether lovely, and a perſon moſt worthy; moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be admired and deſired by the Sons and Daughters of Men, becauſe he gave himſelf for them, and not for the Angels that fell from Heaven.</p>
            <p>Sir, They that find him, find Life, they find Spiritual Life, and ſhall have the Comforts of this Life, and a well grounded hope and a full aſſurance of an Eternal Life. They that find Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Life, will obtain Favour of the Lord,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40139:20"/>whoſe loving kindneſs is better than life, or all the delights of this World; becauſe Sir, it is the Fountain and the Foundation of all true Honour and Happineſs, that Men and Angels are capable to enjoy; yet this great Lord and King, the Jews was ſo unwiſe as to ſlight and undervalue him: They gave him a Crown of Thorns, who only can give them and all the Sons of Men a Crown of Glory. They ſlighted him, who was a better King than <hi>David,</hi> a Wiſer King than <hi>Solomon,</hi> a greater and a better Prophet than <hi>Moſes,</hi> a higher and a greater Prieſt than <hi>Aaron.</hi> all Kings, Prieſts, Apoſtles, Prophets and Martyrs Sir; all Righteous and Holy Men; all Wiſe, Strong, Rich and Learned Men, that are, that have been, or ever will be in the World; they have their Wiſdom, their Power and their Strength, their Honours, their Riches, their great and high Places from him, by his permiſſion, and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his will and pleaſure. To him all muſt give an account, for their health, ſtrength and liberty, and all the means of grace they have enjoyed; and what improvement they have made of his Word, and of his Spirit, which he has con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued from Generation to Generation, for the Information and Reformation of all Nations. Sir, He is able and willing to ſave unto the uttermoſt all that come unto him, Jews and Gentiles, Bond and Free, Male and Female, be they where they will and who they will; for there is no name under Heaven, where by any can be ſaved from Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, from everlaſting Wrath and Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40139:20"/>but by him who is the Way, the Truth and the Life: He is near unto all that call upon him in Truth, for the Prayer of the Upright is his Delight. They that ſeek him, Sir, with their whole Heart, Soul, and Strength, will find him and all good things with him, and in him; that which Eye hath not ſeen, nor Ear hath not heard; nor the Heart of Man is not able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive: For the Heavens, the Earth, and the Sea, and all the Fulneſs that is in them, they are his, for all things were made by him and for him, that are in Heaven and in the Earth, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be Thrones or Dominions, or Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities, or Powers; for by his Wiſdom and Power the whole Creation doth conſiſt. For it pleaſed the Father of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, Sir, that in him, in his onely beloved Son, ſhould all Fulneſs dwell; Fulneſs of Merit, and of Spirit; Fulneſs of Wiſdom, and of Power; Fulneſs of Righteouſneſs and Holineſs; and Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of all Grace and Glory; to make all that come unto him Wiſe, Strong, Rich, Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and moſt Happy. But they that will not, Sir, deny themſelves, overcome themſelves, and lay out themſelves, to come unto him; they will not enjoy themſelves in the midſt of many En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments in the World. But, Sir, Their Lives will be uncomfortable to themſelves, and unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to others; becauſe they cannot be fruitful in good Works, till they come to Chriſt, ſtay with him, and abide in him; then they will be uſeful and fruitful in their Generation, for the good of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:40139:21"/>many in the Nation: then, Sir, they will come to be Plants of Renown, and will flouriſh in the Courts of Gods Houſe, and bring forth pleaſant and profitable Fruit in due time and ſeaſon, that will revive and refreſh the City of God, which is the Church of Chriſt in <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> yea, throughout the whole World.</p>
            <p>But Sir, Unprofitable Branches, that be in his Vineyard, that will not bring forth the Fruits of Righteouſneſs, which is Faith, Love, and Obedience; he will take away and cut down as Branches and Trees that cumber the Ground.</p>
            <p>Sir, The Righteous Perſons, be they where they will, they be the moſt Excellent Perſons in the Earth; becauſe they be moſt Fruitful in their Generation, for the great Honour of God, the King, and the Nation. The Lord loveth the Righteous, let who will hate them; he knows the worth of them, they are, Sir, his Plants of Renown, his Glory and his Crown, and the Labour and Travel of his Soul. The Lord that loveth the Righteous doth preſerve them, and watch over them as his Treaſure; becauſe in them he takes pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Sir, They be a Foundation to a Nation, and do many times preſerve a Nation from Deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The Righteous Perſons, Sir, ſhould be minded and regarded by the Sons of Men, becauſe they be the Light of the World for them. The Righteous Perſons are moſt uſeful and fruitful, for they be the Salt of the Earth, and a City on a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40139:21"/>Hill: They be Men of Wonder, and ſometimes Men of Thunder. Are they not as fair as the Moon, as Clear as the Sun, and as Terrible as an Army with Banners; becauſe they be ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of his might. Sir, In the Righteous Lord that loveth Righteouſneſs, I have both Wiſdom and Power, Righteouſneſs and Strength: Therefore let not any be offended, but let every one labour to be amended, that ſo the times may be the better for them, and many the better for the times; for the Lord he waits to be gracious, and doth not delight in the death of Sinners; but had rather that they would turn and live to him and for him, and then they will for ever live with him; in whoſe preſence is fulneſs of Joy, and at whoſe right hand are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for evermore; that will make amends for all the Tryals, Troubles, Loſſes, Croſſes, and Reproaches, they can meet withal in this life. Sir, This is high and honourable work, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, profitable, and delightſome work; victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, glorious, and crowning work, that will crown the God of Heaven with much Glory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Sons of Men; and our Royal and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Sovereign <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> with great Honour and Power over them, over all Heathen and Popiſh Kings, Prieſts, Princes and Emperors in the World; which will be for the great Honour, Peace, Profit, and Comfort, of all Loyal and Faithful Magiſtrates and Miniſters of the Goſpel in all Nations, that have been for a long time ſlighted and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valued
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40139:22"/>by a Gain-ſaying, Proud, Stubborn, and Rebellious Generation, that have acted againſt Law and Religion; againſt Goſpel and Reaſon: Out of Pride and Contention, they have cauſed Sedition and Treaſon, Wars, and great Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; but the Expectation of ſuch Men will in due time periſh, becauſe they truſt to an Arm of Fleſh, and make Lies their Refuge; but the Hope of the Righreous is Gladneſs, becauſe he truſts in the Lord, in the Lord <hi>Jehovah;</hi> who can and will in this Generation, for the Peace and Proſperity of many Nations, bring Order out of Confuſion, Light out of Darkneſs, and Good out of Evil; when vain has been the help of Man; yea, of many Wiſe, Strong, Rich, and Learned Men, to bring it about; but vain is not the help of the God of Heaven, who has all Power in his own hand, and the whole Creation at command.</p>
            <p>Sir, It is in vain for Men of this Opinion, or that Opinion, for to complain the times are ſad, when that by their ſtrife and contentions they have made them ſo bad. It is Pride that has cauſed Contention, and Contention Seperation from the Government of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which ought not, and would not have been, if that they had minded and regarded the Peace and the Proſperity of the City and the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Great has been the Miſchief that Separation has made in this Generation; in three Ancient and Renowned Nations, as <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Has not Separation cauſed Mutiny,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40139:22"/>and Mutiny Sedition, and Sedition Rebellion, and Rebellion great Diſorder and Confuſion, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many Perſons and Families in theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; to the ſhame of the Proteſtant Religion, and the Government of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> ſo that the times have been the worſe for ſuch Men, and many the worſe for them; but there is no time too late for that Man that is wiſe in Heart, for to cauſe ſuch Men by the Wiſdom and Power of God for to ſmart.</p>
            <p>The Heart of the Wiſe, Sir, teacheth his Mouth, and addeth Learning to his Lips. The wiſe in heart will be called prudent, now Wiſdom dwells with Prudence, which will enable a Man for to hearken unto Counſel, and to attain unto great Counſels; ſo as to know when and how in due time and ſeaſon, for to Counſel Councellors, and to inform Senators; not onely what may be done, but what is beſt to be done; for the great Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, the Peace, and the Proſperity of a King and Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Sir, A King and a Kingdom, may ſtand in need of a Parliament, and an Army of Men; but the Lord of Hoſts, who is the King of Glory, and the Prince of Peace, ſtands not in need of any of them; but can work with them or without them, when and by whom he pleaſe, for to manifeſt his Wiſdom and Power among the Sons of Men; for the great Honour and Exaltation of a Kings Perſon, and the great Joy, Peace, and proſperity of many Nations; which will be brought about in this Generation, for <hi>Englands</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:40139:23"/>great Honour and Exaltation, to the Worlds Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration.</p>
            <p>O great is the Wiſdom and Power of God in Man, with Man, and for Man; when and by whom he pleaſe for to make bare his Arm; that ſo all the Glory may redound to him, and that no Fleſh ſhould glory before him; becauſe all the Sons of Men, have their Wiſdom, their Power, and their Strength from him, that is comfortable to themſelves and profitable to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; for both the preparation of the Heart, and the anſwer of the Tongue, it is from the Lord: For the way of Man is not in himſelf; it is not in Man that walketh for to direct his ſteps, much leſs to order his thoughts; but the ſteps of a good Man, and ſo his thoughts are ordered by the Lord, and he delighteth in his way; for the way of the Lord is ſtrength to upright, but deſtruction will be to the workers of iniquity, in this Generation, to their great ſhame and condemnation; who are for ſtrife and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, ſedition and treaſon; for wars and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. Therefore let all them that be wiſe, be lovers of peace, and workers of righteouſneſs, and then the Lord, who is a lover of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, will encourage them, aſſiſt them, and reward them.</p>
            <p>Let all labour to be wiſe in heart, becauſe that they among the Sons of Men, will beſt underſtand the Mind of the God of Heaven; they will know how to do his will, and keep in his love and favour, which is better than life, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40139:23"/>all the delights of this World; but the wiſdom that is in the World, among too many of the Sons of Men, it is fooliſhneſs, and doth many times end in madneſs, becauſe they do not make the Word of God their Rule, his Spirit their Guid, and his Glory their Aim; but they that do, will never want a wiſe Councellor, and a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Comforter.</p>
            <p>Sir, In the work of Faith, and in the labour of Love, for the Peace and Proſperity of many Perſons in all Nations; I ſhall for the preſent take my leave, and ſhall remain your true and loving Friend <hi>John Varney,</hi> a Member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and of the City of <hi>London,</hi> a Subject to his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and Servant to the God of all Wiſdom, Power, and Strength; who can do what he will, and work with whom he will, among the Sons of Men, to manifeſt his Wiſdom and PoWer over rhem; that ſo all Strife, Contention, and Wars through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole World may ceaſe, and amoug all People in all Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ons <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Trade, great Joy, and a laſting Peace: Therefore Glory, and great Glory be given to the moſt high, from Men and Angels, and that continually; foe his great Wiſdom, Power, Glory, any Majeſty; and great Honour and Renown, grreat Joy, Peace and Proſperity, from the moſt High, upon <hi>Englands</hi> Royal Majeſty, upon his Royal Perſon, and all his Royal Relations; that ſo he and they may long live to Reign for God and with God, among the Sons of Men, for the great Joy and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40139:24"/>Proſperity of them; and at laſt for ever with him, among the Holy Angels in his Kingdom of Heaven. Amen, Amen, let all Loyal and Faithful Subjects in <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſay and pray: yea, all Perſons, in all Nations, that do love the Peace and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of their own Souls, and the Comfort of their Lives.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Auguſt 30th.</hi> 1680.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>
               <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>S.</hi>
            </trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:40139:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
